# Sai Bhanuj Tatineni

+1 4802286932 • <u>statine2@asu.edu</u> • <u>LinkedIn</u> 1720 E Broadway Rd, Tempe, Arizona, 85282

### INTRODUCTION

Graduated with Master's in Computer Science from Arizona State University with approximately 3.5 years of professional experience in Full Stack Development. Strong background in software engineering, with expertise in algorithms and web technologies. Effective problem-solving abilities, good interpersonal skills, and strong written and verbal communication skills. Ability to work both individually and as part of a team.

### **EDUCATION**

Master of Science in Computer Science
Arizona State University, Tempe, AZ
Bachelor of Technology in Electronics and Computer Engineering

August 2021 - May 2023 CGPA: 3.6/4.0 June 2016 - April 2020 CGPA: 3.91/4.0

#### TECHNICAL SKILLS

SASTRA Deemed University, India

- **Programming Languages**: C#, Java, JavaScript, TypeScript, Python, C, C++
- **Topics:** Design of Algorithms, Microservices, Data Structures, OOPS Concepts, RESTful services, DBMS, Object Oriented Programming, Cloud Architecture, Agile, Software development methodologies, SDLC concepts, unit, and integration testing, and Relational DBs
- Web Development: HTML5, CSS3, Bootstrap, Node.js, React.js, Angular.js, APIs, Django, Spring boot, JSP, PHP, GO
- Databases: MongoDB, Oracle, MySQL, PostgreSQL, SQL & MQL, DynamoDB, Apache Cassandra
- Tools and Frameworks: Android, Jira, Postman, Version control systems like, Git, GitHub, Confluence, AWS, Docker, Apache Spark, KAFKA Hadoop, Windows, Linux/Ubuntu, SonarQube, Visual Studio Team Services, Eclipse, Amazon Web Services (EC2, AppSync, API Gateway, Lambda, S3, DynamoDB, SQS), Jenkins, DevOps, Kubernetes

#### TECHNICAL CERTIFICATIONS

- **AWS Solutions Architect Associate:** Gained knowledge in designing and implementing scalable, reliable, and cost-effective solutions on the Amazon Web Services (AWS) cloud platform.
- Algorithms specialization by Tim Rough gardener: Offered on Coursera by Stanford it covers the whole algorithmic design and approach using various data structures to design and develop software algorithms and solutions.

# PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

#### Citizens Bank, Phoenix, Arizona: Software Engineer

June 2023 – present

**Technologies:** Spring Boot, Java, MySQL, Postman, GIT, Microservices, Kafka, Spring batch, Spring Schedulers, Hibernate JPA, JWT authentication, Maven, RESTful Web services, Microservices, J2EE, Jenkins, APIs, Dependency Injection, KAFKA queue topics, Unit, and Integration testing, SDLC development cycles, Deployment tools.

- Developed Spring Boot web service modules adhering to Microservice architecture, reducing development time by 20% while enhancing security with JWT authentication.
- Collaborated on the Fraud detection team, integrating Orbograph for image processing and handling over 10,000 check images monthly, storing results in a MySQL database.
- Implemented an efficient image processing system, reducing processing time by 30% and optimizing data transfer using Kafka queue topics.
- Utilized Spring Batch and Spring Schedulers to boost processing throughput by 40%, loading check Image data into MySQL tables efficiently with Hibernate.
- Designed and implemented a rules service engine to validate scores, ensuring that image scores meet benchmark criteria and detecting potential fake check deposits to store it in database mapped to check data.
- Managed a complex Oracle database with 30 tables, optimizing query performance by 20%, and ensured a 100% security compliance rating during deployment using Jenkins in an Agile environment with Jira.

## Amazon.com, Inc., Seattle, Washington: Software Development Engineering Intern

**June 2022 – May 2023** 

**Technologies:** Alexa Skill Development Programming, NodeJS, Python, REST services, DynamoDB, CDK and LPT pipelines, AWS services, Unit, and Integration testing, SDLC development cycles, Deployment tools.

- Worked with Alexa internationalization (i18n) team, successfully addressing technical debt by implementing new solution, reducing complexities in project by almost 50% and decreasing code refactoring needs by 30%.
- Led end-to-end project execution, from requirement gathering to project deployment, utilizing complete design documentation with architecture, flow, and sequence diagrams, resulting in accelerated development processes.

- Developed "Language Settings" skill for Alexa using Alexa Skill Development Kit (ASK), Python, and DynamoDB, enabling
  customers to switch locale settings and implemented functionality for customers to request desired settings on command
  which resulted in a 75% increase in satisfaction rate when customer feedback is simulated.
- Hosted Skill Lambda through CDK pipeline from previous LPT pipeline implementation, reducing deployment time by 40% and enabling independent skill coding and development, saving 15 hours per week.
- Coded robust unit and integration tests with 95% code coverage, including a canary system for regular skill invocation every 15 minutes, ensuring comprehensive functionality testing and integration of each intent handler.
- Went through daily standup calls with team members. Completed various check-in meetings with manager and provided feedback on where improvements are necessary by filling out review documents.

Arizona State University, Tempe, Arizona: Client Services Assistant (Full stack development) August 2021 – June 2022 Technologies: HTML5, CSS3, Bootstrap, JavaScript, TypeScript, Java, Spring boot, Kafka, GIT NodeJS, AngularJS, SQL DB, JSON, XML, RESTful Services, APIs, Single Page Application (SPA) development, Dependency Injection, Reactive forms for form validations Postman, load balancing, Unit, and Integration Testing.

- Helped in project for efficient file management system, processing and organizing forms submitted by over 1000 new international students for official college use and tracking.
- Developed and deployed Single Page Applications (SPA) using AngularJS, Typescript, Spring Boot, Java, HTML5, CSS3, and Bootstrap 3 for a diverse range of projects.
- Designed and implemented reusable complex nested components, including Pop-Ups and Navigation, resulting in a 30% reduction in development time for subsequent projects.
- Implemented comprehensive form validations, resulting in a 98% reduction in data entry errors and improving data accuracy.
- Created Services for seamless communication between components, enhancing overall application performance and reducing API response times by 25%.
- Utilized Maven for streamlined build management, designed and maintained MySQL databases with over 10 tables, conducted extensive API testing with Postman, and ensured code collaboration and version control using GIT throughout project development.

### Cognizant Technology Solutions, India: Programmer Technology Analyst

**January 2020 – August 2021** 

**Technologies:** HTML5, CSS3, Bootstrap, JavaScript, NodeJS, ReactJS, AngularJS, React – Redux, ExpressJS, jQuery, AJAX, MongoDB, SQL DB, JSON, XML, RESTful Web services design and implementation, Reactive forms for form validations, APIs, Postman, load balancing, Unit, and Integration Testing.

- Proficient in MERN stack technology and REST APIs, gained through comprehensive training and collaboration within a team of 18 members, fostering excellent cross-team collaboration skills.
- Constructed advanced search, sort, filter, and pagination functionalities for an employee record keeping webpage for around 1000 employees and backend Rest services with easily manageable GUI.
- Designed and coded 10+ flexible front-end template models using React and JavaScript, empowering clients to effortlessly
  adapt and leverage the models, resulting in a 30% reduction in development time, high code reusability, and seamless
  application scaling as more than 15 new features were added.
- Contributed to the development and maintenance of a timesheet application, leveraging React JS, Node JS, jQuery, and Mongo DB, resulting in recognition for completing 80% of the assignment within a cohort of 100 people.
- Widgets using React-Redux, React-i18n, NodeJS, HTML, and CSS for internal tools used by PepsiCo employees, demonstrating a high level of technical proficiency and delivering valuable solutions.
- Followed Agile based approach for delivering projects on time with a SCRUM master supervising over us. Used Jira to keep track of the ongoing tasks and how the approach is going on.
- Received an appreciation bonus for being the best scorer in my training cohort of 100 members during training.

### RELEVANT PROJECTS

## E-bookstore with working server - MERN stack

Technologies: HTML5, CSS3, Bootstrap, JavaScript, jQuery, React JS, Node JS, Express JS, Postman, Mongo DB

• Created responsive online bookstore with real-time updates. Features include user registration, login, database storage for 10,000+ users, 50,000+ books, and admin mode.

#### Geo Spatial analysis on large scale data using SparkSOL

Technologies: Hadoop, Apache Spark, GeoSpark API, AWS EC2, PostgreSQL, MySQL, SQL database, Databases

• Engineered Apache Spark's Spark SQL to identify the top 50 NYC hot zones with GeoSpark. Programmed Spark API for transport analysis, using AWS EC2 SSH connections across instances.

# **AWS Image Classification (IaaS – Infrastructure as Service)**

Technologies: AWS Cloud, Deep Learning, Load balancer, FLASK framework, Boto3, SSL Libraries, Python Scripting

• Implemented AWS cloud app for Image Recognition as a Service. Utilized deep learning, load balancer, Flask, Boto3, and AWS resources (EC2, SQS, S3) for secure image processing and user-friendly interface.